<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>online | Daniel Molina profile</title>
    <link>/tags/online/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/online/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>online</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 22:45:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>online</title>
      <link>/tags/online/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>About online teaching</title>
      <link>/post/online_teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 22:45:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/online_teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These days we have to be enclosed in our houses by the coronavirus (COVID-19),
so in my University (in Granada) as the others in Spain, we had to became
in &lt;em&gt;online teaching expert&lt;/em&gt; in a weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the courses we have following different approaches: Additional written
material, several short videos about the materials, or conferences for
giving the courses by video-conferences. All options have its advantages and
drawbacks. However, because I like the feedback with the students (for instance,
to make several examples in code about the concepts in my programming course),
I have finally decided to give the course by video-conference. For
recommendation of my university I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://meet.google.com/&#34;&gt;google meet&lt;/a&gt;, used also for the other
teachers in the course. Personally, I prefer &lt;a href=&#34;https://meet.jit.si/&#34;&gt;Jitsi&lt;/a&gt;, not only it is open source,
but it also it is comparable in features to the google option, it is a great
option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A part of the teaching by video-conference, I have put all the slides in the
Moodle of the courses (actually, it was previously there), and I will try to put
some Quiz to allow students to have a better feedback about their knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem has been to have a deaf student. The video-conference is not
good, and I have spent several days trying several tools to automatic caption
the voice, but in Spanish too many tools do not give a good performance (they
have a lot of errors), finally the best option was &lt;a href=&#34;https://abilityconnect.ua.es/?lang=en&#34;&gt;Ability Connect&lt;/a&gt;, a tool from
University of Alicante (Spain) for that. Unfortunately, sometimes it freezes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people should think that I will have less work, but actually the situation
have put me more work in teaching. It is good to learn new skills, but it takes
a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
