<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>teaching | Daniel Molina profile</title>
    <link>/tags/teaching/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>teaching</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 22:08:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>teaching</title>
      <link>/tags/teaching/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Julia journey</title>
      <link>/post/julia_journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 22:08:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/julia_journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I am going to tell my Julia journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have read about Julia but not actually use it before version 0.7 just before
1.0. I work on Machine Learning and stochastic optimization (with evolutionary
computation). In Machine Learning (and Deep Learning) I work nicely with Python
(Scikit-learn and Keras/PyTorch). However, in optimization I usually did
prototype in Python, and later have to translate to C++ for performance (well,
not while the function evaluation takes too much). Now I starting using Julia
for these algorithms (I prefer it a lot against Numpy). For ML I am actually
testing options with Julia
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alan-turing-institute/MLJ.jl&#34;&gt;MLJ.jl&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FluxML/Flux.jl&#34;&gt;Flux&lt;/a&gt; mainly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main problem is the lack of examples/tutorials in the documentation for
several packages. Also, some missing functionality. I am going to explain it
with an example. I did a small website in Julia to receive a file and transform
it (for learning, I have experience in other technologies like Python/JS, ..)
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pradofacil.danimolina.net/&#34;&gt;http://pradofacil.danimolina.net/&lt;/a&gt;. I did it using Frankling have to create my
own website, it was nice. The server side I have two problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTTP.jl is simple but not very complete, I have to create my own function to
extract the POST parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to have error messages in two different languages (English and
Spanish), but the Gettext package did required Python, and I do not want to
install it in the server only for that. So, I create my own package
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dmolina/SimpleTranslations.jl&#34;&gt;SimpleTranslation.jl&lt;/a&gt; to
translate easy messages in a simple way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually I create scripts, but in Julia the time required to load the packages
make them slower than similar to Python. In order to reduce that problem I
recently created &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dmolina/DaemonMode.jl&#34;&gt;DaemonMode.jl&lt;/a&gt;
package, that got a great interest (even it was mentioned in JuliaCon 2020!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good and bad:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;good: How easily is to create packages, and register it. The syntax, and many
great packages: DataFrames, Plots, &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;bad: documentation of several packages. There is the API, but learning to use
them usually implies several tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise, it is a great language. When you use it, sometimes to affort small
problems due to a not too mature ecosystem, but the evolution is clearly to
best. For sure I will use it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first Julia Package</title>
      <link>/post/moodlequestions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 23:54:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/moodlequestions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For online teaching I use Moodle. I have a lot of experience using it (for more
than 10 years). Unfortunately, the software could be improved a lot. My main
complains are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can import the grades using an Excel file. However, you cannot import the
comments.  I like to give comment to explain the reason of the qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Quiz is potent, but the creation of questions is very slow. Also, in my
University several teachers have historically used another software. However,
Moodle is unable to import these questions (in a different XML format).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to solve the second one, and in conjunction with my interest in Julia,
I have created a package: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dmolina/MoodleQuestions.jl&#34;&gt;MoodleQuestions&lt;/a&gt;. Not only it is able to export from
the previous software, but it is also able to create the questions in a
MoodleXML from a more intuitive file, in text file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;input-text-file-format&#34;&gt;Input text file format&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This package is able to read a text file. The format has been designed to be as simple and readable as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34;&gt; * Category 1

Question 1

- Option 1.1.
- Option 1.2.
+ Option 1.3.

 * Category 2

Question 2

+ Option 2.1.
- Option 2.2.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sentences starting with * is a new category, with the name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sentences without *, +, or - are the text of the question. It is expected to
be from only one line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sentences starting with - or + and the different answers for the previous
question. The - means that the answer is false, and the + means that the
sentence is the right answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answers in the question are shuffle, except when one of the word of A, B,
&amp;hellip; is used. In these cases, the order of the options is maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, to create a text file with the questions in that format is a lot
easier than using the web interface of Moodle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-experience-creating-a-package&#34;&gt;My experience creating a package&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have experience creating a PyPI package in Python, and I only can say that
creating a Julia package is a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there are packages like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/invenia/PkgTemplates.jl&#34;&gt;PkgTemplates&lt;/a&gt; that create all the structure of
the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because in Julia you can add a non-official package adding the github url,
you can use the package working (and share it) without have to register it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tests can be tested very easily with &lt;a href=&#34;https://travis-ci.com/dmolina/MoodleQuestions.jl&#34;&gt;Tracis CI&lt;/a&gt;, for different Julia
version and Operative System (it detected an error only in Windows). However,
because Julia is not officially supported and the Sandbox implies to install
all required packages for each time, the time in the test implies a lot of
time, more than 1m30 in several versions. At least, it gives the tranquility
of working in different julia versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation can be done very easily with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JuliaDocs/Documenter.jl&#34;&gt;Documenter.jl&lt;/a&gt;, and it publish
in Github Pages (the only problem was to define the DOCUMENTER_KEY
environment variable, but the error was clear).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Registration is was very simple. Originally, you had to do a Pull Request
to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JuliaRegistries/General&#34;&gt;https://github.com/JuliaRegistries/General&lt;/a&gt; repository. However,
nowadays you should use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JuliaRegistries/Registrator.jl&#34;&gt;https://github.com/JuliaRegistries/Registrator.jl&lt;/a&gt;,
that with a simple web interface it will do the PR for you (only the URL is
required).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise, the experience has been very positive. In my opinion, you are a
lot more lost than in Python when you have to create your first setup.py, and it
is easier to follow the good practices of Continous Integration with tests and
Documentation. Also, there is a great presentation at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QVmU29rCjaA&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QVmU29rCjaA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About online teaching</title>
      <link>/post/online_teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 22:45:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/online_teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These days we have to be enclosed in our houses by the coronavirus (COVID-19),
so in my University (in Granada) as the others in Spain, we had to became
in &lt;em&gt;online teaching expert&lt;/em&gt; in a weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the courses we have following different approaches: Additional written
material, several short videos about the materials, or conferences for
giving the courses by video-conferences. All options have its advantages and
drawbacks. However, because I like the feedback with the students (for instance,
to make several examples in code about the concepts in my programming course),
I have finally decided to give the course by video-conference. For
recommendation of my university I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://meet.google.com/&#34;&gt;google meet&lt;/a&gt;, used also for the other
teachers in the course. Personally, I prefer &lt;a href=&#34;https://meet.jit.si/&#34;&gt;Jitsi&lt;/a&gt;, not only it is open source,
but it also it is comparable in features to the google option, it is a great
option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A part of the teaching by video-conference, I have put all the slides in the
Moodle of the courses (actually, it was previously there), and I will try to put
some Quiz to allow students to have a better feedback about their knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem has been to have a deaf student. The video-conference is not
good, and I have spent several days trying several tools to automatic caption
the voice, but in Spanish too many tools do not give a good performance (they
have a lot of errors), finally the best option was &lt;a href=&#34;https://abilityconnect.ua.es/?lang=en&#34;&gt;Ability Connect&lt;/a&gt;, a tool from
University of Alicante (Spain) for that. Unfortunately, sometimes it freezes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people should think that I will have less work, but actually the situation
have put me more work in teaching. It is good to learn new skills, but it takes
a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to CMake</title>
      <link>/post/intro_cmake/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 22:11:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/intro_cmake/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my last course, I decided to give a small introduction about CMake. The
reason is that, although we teach them Make, the majority of students do not use
them in their programs. In fact, many times they create a &amp;ldquo;makefile&amp;rdquo; program to
pretend they are using &amp;ldquo;make&amp;rdquo;, but actually, it is a bash script.
My intention is to teach them &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmake.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cmake&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to encourage them to use an automatic tool
for compiling, expecting they use it more, by its simpler syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The english version is:&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/capture_english.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/capture_english.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spanish version is:&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/capture_spanish.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/capture_spanish.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the source code (in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hakimel/reveal.js/&#34;&gt;reveal.js&lt;/a&gt;, through &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yjwen/org-reveal/&#34;&gt;org-reveal&lt;/a&gt;) are available at:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dmolina/intro_cmake&#34;&gt;https://github.com/dmolina/intro_cmake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Python for Business Intelligence</title>
      <link>/post/python_bi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 18:18:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/python_bi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago I started my first teaching day, replacing a teacher that has
still not gone to Ceuta (because the temporal contract was offered to many
people, and all of them refuse it). Do not worry, they will have the material, I
said to myself, naïvely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, my Phd. advisor, the coordinator of the course, has decided to replace
the practice classes from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.knime.com/&#34;&gt;Knime&lt;/a&gt; to Python using the different tools availables.
The reason? Because the Python, with R, are very popular in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_science&#34;&gt;Data Science&lt;/a&gt;. Also,
in Python there are very good tools for data analysis (like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.numpy.org/&#34;&gt;numpy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://pandas.pydata.org/&#34;&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt;) or
machine learning (&lt;a href=&#34;http://scikit-learn.org/stable/&#34;&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;hellip;). It seems a good idea, but I have not
material, and I have only two days :-O.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more, I had still no access to the Moodle for the material of the course.
So, after a very busy Saturday, I finished including a material,  in
&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/dmolina/es_intro_python&#34;&gt;http://github.com/dmolina/es_intro_python&lt;/a&gt;, with interesting references and an
install introduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I use a very curious tool, &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitpitch.com&#34;&gt;https://gitpitch.com&lt;/a&gt;, that allow to create
slides from a markdown file from the repository github, &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitpitch.com/dmolina/es_intro_python/master?grs=github&amp;amp;t=moon&#34;&gt;Slides using Pitch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final experience was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very few students, so it was very relaxed because you can solve the problems
for each student. However, using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anaconda.com/&#34;&gt;anaconda&lt;/a&gt; there is few problems (and the .
In prevision of the big size of the anaconda distribution, my downloaded
version was copied by USB Disk to students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://jupyter.org/&#34;&gt;jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt; allow to test the python code without installing or
learning an IDE (later they can install which they prefer, but for teaching
you do not need any of them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to prepare exercises, because if not, you talk and show and you can
finished in few minutes a material that takes you many hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have only a weekend for preparing material, I must have already strong
knowledge about the topic (fortunately,  it was my case). If not, you will not
be confident teaching it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the second day, I was preparing another slide for teaching pandas (with the
most useful operations, by my experience), available as pdf format here:
&lt;a href=&#34;./slides/slides_pandas.pdf&#34;&gt;slides_pandas.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (In a future post, I will say as I
prepare my slides using Emacs+Org-mode). &lt;em&gt;Unfortunately&lt;/em&gt;, the new teacher was
ready,  and I have to finish my courses using python for BI.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
